Guide to the AFSCME, Local 420, Hospital Workers Photographs PHOTOS.212
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
AFSCME, Local 420, Hospital Workers Photographs
1978-2002
1990-1999
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
AFSCME. Local 420 (Municipal Hospital Workers Union) (New York, N.Y.)
Charles, Carmen
PHOTOS.212
27 Linear Feet
AFSCME Local 420 represents a wide range of non-medical personnel in New York City's municipal hospitals and health centers. Among its members are registered and practical nurses, nurses' aides, pharmacy technicians, orderlies, cafeteria staff, clerical assistants and maintenance workers, many of them African-American or Hispanic. The Local has been active in the civil rights movement, in African-American and Hispanic community affairs, in campaigns to oppose privatization and budget cuts in public hospitals, and securing better pay, benefits and training opportunities for non-professional hospital workers. The Collection includes dated images, mainly black and white and color prints, from 1979 to 2002 (and some earlier undated images from the 1970s), but most are from the 1980s and 1990s. NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
(Ca. 12, 300 b&w prints; ca. 3, 24 color prints; ca. 450 35mm and 8x10 b&w negatives; ca. 400 35mm color negatives; 12 color transparencies; ca. 9,000 slides)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by AFSCME, Local 420, under an agreement with Local President Carmen Charles, in 2004. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2004.021, NPA.2005.172, and NPA.2007.025.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
AFSCME Local 420, Hospital Workers, represents a wide range of non-professional workers employed in the New York City municipal hospitals and health centers. Until the 1950s city hospital workers, many of them black or Hispanic, were among the lowest paid of municipal workers and remained outside the organized labor movement. Registered and practical nurses, aides, orderlies, clerical assistants, laundry workers, maintenance workers and truck drivers often worked in unsanitary even dangerous conditions, under intense pressure. Their concerns, when hospital organizing began, were not only with pay, benefits and opportunities for advancement, but also with issues of respect and dignity on the job. The city hospital system, consisting of 21 hospitals spread throughout the five boroughs, each of them a vast complex of wards, clinics and offices, offered daunting obstacles to union organizing. In 1955 the fledgling Local 420, recently consolidated from several older units comprising AFSCME, District Council 37's Joint Board of Hospital Workers, had fewer than 500 members citywide.
AFSCME District Council 37 director Jerry Wurf assigned several dynamic organizers to the Local, with a view to increasing its size and challenging Teamsters Local 237, which was then the most influential union in the city hospital system. One of the key organizers in the early years was James Butler. Despite determined opposition from administrators, the Local grew steadily and some basic improvements in working conditions were achieved. By 1964, the Local had grown to nearly 5,000 members, while the Teamsters claimed 6,500. New DC 37 head Victor Gotbaum stepped up the drive among hospital workers, and assigned his trusted assistant Lillian Roberts, to the campaign. Roberts promised on-the-job training programs to move workers into better-paying jobs, decent treatment from, supervisors, fair grievance procedures and tough and honest collective bargaining. Gotbaum, meanwhile, enlisted the support of A. Philip Randolph, Bayard Rustin, George Meany, the New York City Central Labor Council and a number of AFL-CIO union presidents on Local 420's behalf. By the fall of 1965 Gotbaum was ready to take on the Teamsters in a representation election, and in December 1965 city hospital workers, voting in the largest representation election in New York history, chose Local 420 as their union. The following year the Local negotiated an historic agreement with the City, providing for pay increases, welfare fund contributions by the City, and a dues check-off. The election gave DC 37 a majority in the hospitals and also among non-uniformed city workers; this success spawned new gains in organizing, and by the end of 1966 the Council represented more than 80,000 city employees. Over the next few years the Local continued to make steady gains through bargaining, but had continuing concerns over waste, inefficiency in management, understaffing and deplorable conditions at municipal hospitals, while city officials made more and more concessions to private hospitals. Steady pressure from DC37 blocked plans by the Lindsay administration to lease or fully privatize several hospitals. But this was only the first salvo in what was to become a continuing struggle to defend public hospitals and their unionized employees.
In 1972 James Butler was elected president of Local 420, and immediately took on the battle for better pay, benefits and educational opportunities, and against privatization and hospital closings. Butler led the Local through the trying times of citywide fiscal crisis in the mid-1970s and on to a period of greatly increased membership (reaching an estimated total of 14,000 in the early 1990s) and influence. He raised the public profile of the Local through rallies, marches, involvement in community affairs and a firm commitment to national, and even international, campaigns for civil rights and human rights. Butler's militant political agenda was furthered by Local officers such as Secretary-Treasurer (from 1984) Kendreth Smith, Executive Vice-President (from 1996) Sarah Kennedy, Vice-President Alejandro Ruiz, Political Action Chairman, and James Webb, among others.
Under Butler's administration the Local developed an effective newspaper, the City Hospital Worker; supported an award-winning choir, the Voices of Local 420; and participated in the Coalition of Black Trade Unionists, the New York State Black and Puerto Rican Caucus, the Coalition of Labor Union Women, Jesse Jackson's Operation PUSH, the NAACP, the National Urban League, the Southern Christian Leadership Conference's Labor Committee and other labor and civil rights organizations. The Local became a leading force in ASCME DC37's Hospitals Division and in AFSCME's Health Advisory Committee.
As a result of the staunch opposition of Local 420 and DC37, the Giuliani administration was prevented from selling off Coney Island, Elmhurst and Queens hospitals, as a first step toward dismantling the city hospital system. Despite the reluctance of other New York labor leaders to confront a popular mayor, President Butler organized rallies, prayer vigils outside homes of city officials, and a "Freedom Bus," that followed the mayor on the senate campaign trail. A landmark court decision blocked the sale of entire facilities, but Giuliani pushed ahead with drastic cutbacks in funding of the Health and Hospitals Corporation, reallocation of Medicaid funds to private hospitals, closures, and privatization of some hospital services, with the result that the Local's membership dropped to 7,500 and the number of municipal hospitals to 11 by 2001. Clashes between Butler and DC37 executive director Stanley Hill meant that the local could no longer count on firm Council backing in negotiations. In the late 1990s dissent began to grow within the Local, as members questioned lavish expenditures by the leadership, a burdensome dues increase, and plans for a lavish new local headquarters that never materialized.
In December local vice-president Carmen Charles, representing the opposition within the Local, challenged James Butler for the presidency and won, by a narrow margin. Despite repeated challenges to the election result by the Butler slate and inaction by DC 37, Charles's victory was finally confirmed by AFSCME's national Judicial Panel in May 2002. The new administration has embarked on a program of revitalization and reorganization, aimed at defending the some of the city's most vulnerable municipal workers in the chilly climate of the new millennium.
Sources:
Bernard and Jewel Bellush, Union Power and New York: Victor Gotbaum and District Council 37 (New York: Praeger Publishers, 1984).
Deirdre McFadden, "Butler's Last Stand," City Limits Monthly(on-line), November 2001.
Silver Anniversary Celebration of Jim Butler, October 11, 1997 (New York: AFSCME, Local 420, 1997).
Scope and Content Note
Although the Collection contains images from Local 420's parent union, AFSCME-District Council 37, and District Council 37's own parent organization, the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees, as well as a considerable number of images from other organizations, most of the Collection consists of images pertaining to Local 420 itself. The largest number of Collection's the images are black and white prints, followed by color prints, and most images date from the 1990s or are undated. The undated portion of the Collection appears to be largely from the 1980s; it also contains the earliest images in the Collection, a small amount that appears to be from the 1970s; some of the latter document events in the Local's history from the time just before and not long after James Butler was elected president of Local 420 (folder numbers 27, 106, 252, 757, and 758). The large number of photographs (in the Local Officers sub-subseries) of James Butler (and others from the upper levels of the Local's hierarchy) at political and social gatherings and being honored in ceremonies and with awards both inside and outside the union, capture Butler's rise from organizer to influential union president. Of special importance, then, are the images from the Units--the smallest organizational subdivisions of the Local-because they document individuals and activities of the rank and file membership in individual hospitals. The broad concerns of the Local and its parent organizations about national and international as well as New York City labor issues, and about political issues beyond labor, such as apartheid, civil rights, and women's rights, are well-represented in the extensive number of images in the Demonstrations and Rallies sub-subseries. The Personalities sub-subseries encompasses well-known public personalities and celebrities from outside of the Local, at Local events or at gatherings of allied organizations. Other sub-subseries of particular interest are Worksite--which, though small in number, contains valuable images of union members at work--and Other Organizations, which contains images that relate to labor, social, and political organizations with which Local 420 has associated itself (in particular the Coalition of Black Trade Unionists and civil rights organizations such as the NAACP), and Political, which includes images showing important local, state, and national politicians interacting with the union and its leadership, and with other labor leaders. The images in Oversized Mounted Photographs series appear to have been produced for an exhibit or exhibits; almost all are black and white and mounted mostly on foam-board; they range in size from 19 ¾ x 13 inches to 20x30 inches and each has been individually numbered on the back. Smaller prints of many of these same images can be found in other parts of the Collection.
NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged by organization, and then topically/chronologically within each series. Topical sub-subseries include: Celebrations, Committees, Demonstrations and Rallies, Events, Hearings, International Friendship/Solidarity, Local Officers, Meetings, Personalities, Political, Units, and Worksites. Not every series includes all subseries or sub-subseries. Some of the same events are documented in more than one series; therefore researchers searching for a particular event or phenomena will need to examine the entire container list for the collection. Individual folders titles that have been assigned by archivists are enclosed in brackets; those not in brackets are the original titles of the folders in which the photographs were filed when the Collection was received.
Organized into 7 series:
Missing Title
I, Black and white prints
II, Color prints
III, Black and white negatives
IV, Color negatives
V, Color transparencies
VI, Color slides
VII, Oversized (black and white) mounted prints
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Records of AFSCME, DC 37, Local 420 (Wagner #215). For further biographical and historical information on Local 420 and to review the scope and contents of its Records, see Guide to the Records of AFSCME, Local 420, Hospital Workers.
Separated Material
Fifteen plastic and canvas banners have been separated and placed in the Tamiment/Wagner ephemera and artifacts collections; nineteen picket signs have been separated and placed in the Tamiment/Wagner picket signs collection.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Hospitals |x Employees |x Labor unions |z United States.; Black-and-white photographs.; Hospitals |x Job descriptions.; Color slides.; Transparencies.; Color negatives.; New York (N.Y.); Hospitals |z United States |x History.; Nurses.; Hospitals |z New York (State) |z New York.; Color photographs.; Nurses' aides.; Black-and-white negatives.; Health and Hospitals Corporation (New York, N.Y.); AFSCME. District Council 37 (New York, N.Y.); AFSCME; Wurf, Jerry, 1919-; Kennedy, Sarah; Butler, James; AFSCME. Local 420 (Municipal Hospital Workers Union) (New York, N.Y.) -- |v Pictorial works; Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (U.S.); Webb, James; Smith, Kendreth; Ruiz, Alejandro; AFSCME. Local 420 (Municipal Hospital Workers Union) (New York, N.Y.); Charles, Carmen
- Series I: Black and White Prints
  - Subseries A: AFSCME
    - AFSCME 25th Convention (Atlantic City) (06/21/82 -- 06/25/82), Jun 21, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - AFSCME Women's Conference, Oct 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - AFSCME Hawaii, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - AFSCME International Convention, May 8, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - AFSCME Convention Las Vegas, Nevada, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - AFSCME International, Jul 20, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - [AFSCME 33rd International Convention -- Hawaii (8-24-98 - 8-28-98)], Aug 24, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - AFSCME Women's Conference, Jul 3, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - [AFSCME Communication Conference] [1970s?], undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - [AFSCME -- DC 1707], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - AFSCME Indiana, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - AFSCME Women's Regional Conference, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - [DC 1707 Banquet], undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Locals 1597, 420, 1549 Employee Parade, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Subseries B: AFSCME -- District Council 37
    - [Miscellaneous AFSCME Meetings -- dates unknown], undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Kings County Voter Registration, Aug 5, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Women's History Month DC37, Mar 24, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Shortage of Jobs Meeting (Citywide DC37 Meeting), Jan 12, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 420/DC 37 City Meeting, Apr 9, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Hillary Clinton [Speaks at] DC 37, Oct 16, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - DC 37 Layoff Mass Meeting, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - [DC 37 & Local 420 -- Politicians with Union Officials], undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - End the Death Penalty Campaign, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Wurf, Jerry, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Subseries C: Local 420
    - Sub-subseries i: General
      - [Local 420 Contract Settlement], 1991 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - [Contact Sheets -- Miscellaneous Subjects -- includes AFSCME Communication Conference, member portraits, laundry workers, graduations, P.E.O.P.L.E.], undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - [Early 420 History. See Folder #757 for some matching negatives], undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - [Leafleting and Organizing], undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - [Local 420 Members -- Celebrating Contract Victories/Pay Raises?], undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - [Local 420 Members -- Group Shots], undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - [Local 420 Members -- Mostly Portraits], undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Local 420 & NAACP, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - [Local 420 -- Negotiation Session?], undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - [Miscellaneous -- Unidentified unknown], undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - P.E.O.P.L.E. & Local 420, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - [Surveillance], undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - [Voices of 420] 420 Choir, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Voices of 420 [perform at a] Funeral [at a] Church, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Sub-subseries ii: Celebrations
      - [Celebrating Women's History Month], Mar 29, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - [Martin Luther King Jr. Celebration, Memphis, Tenn.], Apr 4, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - [Local 420 Christmas Party], Dec 1, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - Local 420 Children Christmas Party, Dec 19, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - [Local 420 Salutes Black History Month], Feb 24, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - Institutional Dietary Aides Halloween Party/ Butler Honored by DC 1707, Oct 1, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - Hispanic Heritage Month, Oct 15, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - Black History Month Celebration, Feb 11, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - Hispanic Celebration, Oct 8, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - 1st Anniversary of Local 420, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - 8th Anniversary [of] Local 420, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
      - [Banquets], undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - Black History Month Celebration, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
      - Certificate of Appreciation Ceremony, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
      - Martin Luther King Jr. B[irth]day Celebration, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
      - Martin Luther King Jr. Leadership Award Ceremony, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
      - [Miscellaneous Celebrations (retirements, birthdays, awards, honors) [Folder 1 of 2], undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
      - [Miscellaneous Celebrations (retirements, birthdays, awards, honors) [Folder 2 of 2], undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
      - Service Award Ceremony, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Sub-subseries iii: Committees
      - Women's Committee (Local 420) [Probably 1989] (Box 2, Folder 58)
      - Youth Committee, Jun 1999 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Sub-subseries iv: Demonstrations and Rallies
      - Ratify the E.R.A. Campaign, Atlanta, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 60)
      - [Hospital Cutbacks Protest/ March from Sydenham Hospital to the "Harlem State Office Building"], Mar 12, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 61)
      - Newspaper Article(s) Budget Cuts/Hospitals, Jul 1981 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - March on Gracie Mansion for Decent Contract, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 63)
      - Daily News Strike, Dec 1990 (Box 2, Folder 64)
      - Sister Delores Benejan Rally [Probably 1991] (Box 2, Folder 65)
      - Jobs for Justice [Probably 1991] (Box 2, Folder 66)
      - Chief Medical Examiner Office Demonstration for Safety, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 67)
      - Hamlet, May 2, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 68)
      - Apartheid Rally [Spring 1992] (Box 2, Folder 69)
      - [A March on Washington -- "Save Our Cities, Save Our Children"] [Probably 5/16/1992], May 16, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      - Haitian Rally Washington, Sep 9, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 71)
      - [March for Jobs, Justice & Racial Harmony], Apr 4, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      - Jobs for Justice, Apr 14, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 73)
      - Rally CME [Chief Medical Examiner's] Office, Aug 10, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 74)
      - No Lay Off, Mar 28, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 75)
      - Stop Church Burning (Rally), Jul 28, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 76)
      - Health and Hospitals Corporation Rally, Aug 6, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 77)
      - Health and Hospitals Corporation Rally, Oct 10, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 78)
      - WEP ["Workfare"] Worker Rally City Hall [See Folder # 79 for some matching negatives.], Jan 15, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 79)
      - [Justice for Abner Louima -- Preparation for Demonstration and Demonstration. Probably 8/1997.], Aug 1, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 80)
      - [Justice for Abner] Louima Rally, Aug 29, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 81)
      - Gracie Mansion Rally, Oct 8, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 82)
      - Health and Hospitals Corporation Rally [Cafeteria Workers], Oct 30, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 83)
      - Support Strawberry Workers, Nov 25, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 84)
      - No Layoffs Health and Hospitals Corporation Rally, Mar 18, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 85)
      - Gracie Mansion Rally, Mar 31, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 86)
      - Saturday Morning Gracie Mansion, Apr 25, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 87)
      - Health and Hospitals Corporation Rally, Jun 8, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 88)
      - Health and Hospitals Corporation Rally, Jul 16, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 89)
      - 420 Court Albany, Feb 16, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 90)
      - Morning Rally at Gracie Mansion, Mar 18, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 91)
      - Mass Labor Rally (City Hall Park), May 12, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 92)
      - TWU [Transport Workers Union of America] Rally, Dec 8, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 93)
      - Gracie Mansion 3/31 [year unknown], undated (Box 2, Folder 94)
      - [No Layoff/No Pink Slips -- Demonstration at the Sheraton Hotel (snowing). [April 9, year unknown], undated (Box 2, Folder 95)
      - Dr Marcos Prayer Vigil 4/10 [year unknown], undated (Box 2, Folder 96)
      - Members of 420 March in Albany 6/13 [year unknown], undated (Box 2, Folder 97)
      - AFSCME & Local 420 [Support Mushroom Farmers] [See Folder #780 for some matching negatives.], undated (Box 2, Folder 98)
      - [AFSCME Supports the Frontier Hotel Strikers -- Las Vegas; probably 1991-1997], undated (Box 2, Folder 99)
      - Apartheid [See Folder #761 for some matching negatives.], undated (Box 2, Folder 100)
      - ["Arrest Giuliani" Demonstration], undated (Box 2, Folder 101)
      - [COPA Rally? Includes Jesse Jackson Speaking], undated (Box 2, Folder 102)
      - ["Crack Kills" Demonstration], undated (Box 2, Folder 103)
      - DC 2175 Sandhog protest, undated (Box 3, Folder 104)
      - Demonstration in front of City Hall, undated (Box 3, Folder 105)
      - [Early (ca. 1970s) Demonstrations and Rallies -- Miscellaneous], undated (Box 3, Folder 106)
      - Federal Help March, undated (Box 3, Folder 107)
      - Health and Hospitals Corporation Rally [at Gracie Mansion], undated (Box 3, Folder 108)
      - Home Healthcare Workers Campaign, undated (Box 3, Folder 109)
      - Hospital Support Sunday [Rally], undated (Box 3, Folder 110)
      - Justice Now Campaigns, undated (Box 3, Folder 111)
      - Labor and Civil Rights (Dr. King Remembrance), undated (Box 3, Folder 112)
      - Local 420 Supports Local 1199, undated (Box 3, Folder 113)
      - [Mourning the Dealth of Public Hospitals -- Demonstration at the Sheraton Hotel (Autumn?)], undated (Box 3, Folder 114)
      - [No Budget Cuts Rally held in Memorial Baptist Church], undated (Box 3, Folder 115)
      - [No Layoffs Demonstration (in Albany?)], undated (Box 3, Folder 116)
      - [No Layoffs Rally held in Memorial Baptist Church? w/ James Butler, Stanley Hill, & U.S. Representative Charles Rangel. Probably 1990s.], undated (Box 3, Folder 117)